Guide to the Turkish political posters collection, 1943-2016 RL.01311
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Turkish political posters collection
1943-2016 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
RL.01311
23 Linear Feet
Collection comprises 175 Turkish political posters, including three duplicates. There are seven series of posters: Korean War, NATO, Historical significance, Commemoration of Ottoman historical figures, Republican-era historical figures, Leftist, and Presidency of the Turkish Republic. In the first, sixteen posters extoll the achievements of the Turkish Armed Forces command or Turkish Brigade in the Korean War between November 1950 and July 1953. In the second series, one poster represents Turkey's relationship to North Atlantic Treaty Organization (NATO), and another reflects the naval and air force maneuvers of NATO's Southern Command, Greece, and Turkey at Weld Fast in 1953. The third series includes 26 posters that celebrate events of historic national significance and depict international political figures together with Turkish leaders. The fourth series includes four posters that commemorate Ottoman historical figures, including admiral Barbaros Hayrettin, and sultans Mehmet V, Mehmed II, and Selim I. The fifth series includes 14 posters of Repulican-era historical figures, including portraits of World War II generals and political figures. The sixth series contains 63 leftist political posters with political slogans, as well as calls for meetings and demonstrations; most of them date from the second half of the 1970's. The seventh series contains 50 posters issued by the Presidency of the Turkish Republic regarding the failed coup attempt of 15 July 2016.
175 Items
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The Turkish political posters collection was received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as purchases in 2009, 2010, 2017, 2018, and 2019.
Collection Overview
Collection comprises 175 Turkish political posters, including three duplicates. There are seven series of posters: Korean War, NATO, Historical significance, Commemoration of Ottoman historical figures, Republican-era historical figures, Leftist, and Presidency of the Turkish Republic (which features posters issued following the failed 2016 coup).
Turkey -- Armed Forces; Political posters, Turkish; Korean War, 1950-1953 -- Regimental histories -- Turkey; Social movements -- Turkey; Printing -- Political aspects -- Turkey -- History -- 20th century; Symbolism in art; Socialism -- Turkey; Hatay İli (Turkey) -- History; Symbolism in politics -- Turkey; Turkey, Ordu -- History; Turkey -- Military relations; Turkey -- History -- 1960-; Turkey -- History -- 1918-1960; Turkey -- Foreign relations; Communism -- Turkey; Korean War, 1950-1953; Korean War, 1950-1953 -- Posters; Posters; Turkey -- Social conditions -- 1960-; Turkey -- Politics and government -- 1960-1980; World War, 1939-1945 -- Turkey; Coups d'etat -- Turkey; Turkey -- History -- Attempted coup, 2016; Atatürk, Kemal, 1881-1938; Bayar, Celâl, 1883-1986; Corvalán, Luis, 1916-2010; North Atlantic Treaty Organization; Kaypakkaya, İbrahim, d. 1973; İnönü, İsmet, 1884-1973; Dora, Celâl.; Yazıcı, Tahzin; United Nations -- Armed Forces -- Turkey; Türkiye Sosyalist Isçi Partisi; Türkiye Isçi Partisi; Mehmet V, Sultan of the Turks, 1844-1918; Mehmed II, Sultan of the Turks, 1432-1481; Selim I, Sultan of the Turks, 1470-1520; Hayreddin Paşa, Barbaros, -1546; Çakmak, Fevzi, 1876-1950; Omurtag, Salih; Turkey. Cumhurbaşkanlığı
- Korean War Series, 1950-1953
  Scope and Contents note
  Sixteen posters, including 2 duplicates, extoll the achievements of the Turkish Armed Forces command or Turkish Brigade in the Korean War between November 1950 and July 1953. These posters show battle scenes and portraits of Brigadier General Tahzin Yazıcı and assistant Brigade commander Celâl Dora. Another shows an American officer, General Walker, decorating Yazıcı with the Silver Star. Ten of these posters are signed by graphic artists, including M. Işık, Cemal Baki, M. Baki, and Mehmet Tekdal; the remainder are unsigned.
  - Korean War posters (Box 1, Folder 1)
- NATO Series, 1953
  One poster represents Turkey's relationship to North Atlantic Treaty Organization (NATO), and another reflects the naval and air force maneuvers of NATO's Southern Command, Greece, and Turkey at Weld Fast in 1953, which were designed to test the training and co-operation of their forces. Individuals represented in the second poster include military leaders Nurettin Baransel, Willard G. Wyman, Stylianos Kitrilakis, and Alezandros Karadimitropoulos.
  - NATO posters (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Historical Significance Series, 1943-1960
  Twenty-six posters celebrate events of historic national significance and depict international political figures together with Turkish leaders. Within the series, there are seven posters celebrating the annexation of Hatay State into Turkey as Hatay province, one depicting Atatürk and Mustafa İsmet İnönü on the occasion of the 20th anniversary of the Revolution, one showing U.S. President Dwight Eisenhower shaking hands with Celâl Bayar, and another image of Winston Churchill shaking hands with İnönü. Other posters depict women's support of the army and British-Turkish relations. Within this series, 19 posters are signed by artist Mehmet Bakı (some M. Bakı); the others are not signed.
  - Historical Significance posters (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Commemoration of Ottoman Historical Figures Series, undated
  Scope and Contents
  Four posters commemorate Ottoman historical figures, including admiral Barbaros Hayrettin, and sultans Mehmet V, Mehmed II, and Selim I.
  - Ottoman Historical Figures posters (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Republican-era Historical Figures Series, undated
  Fourteen posters of Repulican-era historical figures, including portraits of World War II generals, Greek war, and political figures such as Atatürk (five posters), İnönü (five posters), Fevzi Çakmak (three posters), Salih Omurtag, and Kazim Orbay. Within this series, 11 posters are signed by artist Mehmet Bakı (some M. Bakı); the others are not signed.
  - Republican-era Historical Figures Posters (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Leftist Series, 1970-1978
  Sixty-three leftist political posters (plus one duplicate) with political slogans, as well as calls for meetings and demonstrations. Most date from the second half of the 1970's, a period when the political climate was influenced by inflation, unemployment, and political violence. The slogans attack "fascist" and capitalist politics and denounce poverty. One poster contains a portrait of the Luis Corvalá́n, the former general secretary of the Communist party of Chile. Three others promote "Health Week 1977," which was organized by the Istanbul Tabip Odasi (Istanbul Medical Chamber). Political organizations named on the posters include, but are not limited to, Türkiye Isçi Partisi, Türkiye Sosyalist Isçi Partisi (TSIP), Türkiye Sağlık Işçileri Sendikası. One poster shows a portrait of Ibrahim Kaypakkaya, a well-known political prisoner active in the Communist movement, together with a portrait of of Aşık Emekçi, a singer. In this series symbols such as raised fists, fists smashing a svastika, broken chains, and silhouettes of workers' faces abound.
  - Leftist posters (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Presidency of the Turkish Republic Series, 2016
  50 posters issued by the Presidency of the Turkish Republic regarding 15 Temmuz, the failed coup d'etat attempt of 15 July 2016. The posters all feature the same theme, "respect our destiny and our soldiers," and feature two sizes, 39 x 22.5-inches (but untrimmed) and 28 x 39-inches. One is extra large at 39 x 78-inches.
  - Presidency of the Turkish Republic posters (Folder 8, Folder 7, Folder 9, Tube 1)